A Guide to the René Jules Dubos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA122
Rockefeller Archive Center
René Jules Dubos papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1900-1987 (Bulk:1927-1982)
1927-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Dubos, René J. (René Jules)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA122
60 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
René Jules Dubos (1901-1982), microbiologist and environmentalist, was affiliated with the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, The Rockefeller University, for more than 50 years (1927-1942 and 1944-1982). During this tenure, Dubos made his most significant contribution to the field of antibiotics with the discovery of gramicidin in 1939. The development, identification, cultivation, and analysis of gramicidin encouraged further experimentation in the field of antibiotics.
René Dubos was born on February 20, 1901 in Saint Brice, France. From 1915 to 1919 he was a student at the College Chaptal in Paris and studied at the Institut National Agronomique from 1919-1921. Dubos received his Ph. D. from Rutgers University in 1927. He became a fellow at the RIMR in that same year and served as a professor from 1957 to 1971, becoming professor emeritus, 1971-1982.
Dubos' environmental activism began in the 1950s, when he urged the scientific community to accept social responsibility for the preservation of the environment. His maxim, "think globally, act locally," became the rallying cry for a generation of environmentalists.
Biographical Note
1901 Born February 20, Saint Brice, France
1915-1919 Student, College Chaptal, Paris
1919-1921 Institut National Agronomique, Paris
1924 Came to the United States
1924-1927 Research Assistant in soil microbiology and instructor in bacteriology, New Jersey Experimental Station at Rutgers University
1927 Ph. D. Rutgers University
1927-1928 Fellow Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York
1928-1930 Assistant RIMR
1930-1938 Associate, RIMR
1938-1941 Associate Member, RIMR
1941-1942 Member, RIMR
1942 Resigned
1942-1944 George Fabyan Professor Comparative Pathology and Tropical Medicine, Harvard University
1944-1956 Reappointed member Rockefeller Institute
1957- Professor Rockefeller University
1971- Professor Emeritus, Rockefeller University
1921-1922 Served in the French Army
1922-1924 Served as Assistant editor staff International Institute Agr., Rome
Honorary Degrees
1941 Sc. D. Rochester Univ.
1942 Sc. D. Harvard
1949 Sc. D. Rutgers Univ.
1950 Sc. D. Paris Univ.
1956 Sc. D. New School for Social Research, N.Y.
1956 Sc. D. Rio de Janeiro Univ. Sc. D. Dartmouth
1947 M.D. (Hon.) Liege
1961 M.D. (Hon.) Yeshiva University
1963 M.D. (Hon.) University of Alta
1965 M.D. (Hon.) University of Pennsylvania
1965 M.D. (Hon.) University of California
1966 Hon. Deg. Colby College Carlton College
1968 Hon. Deg. St. Johns University
1969 Hon. Deg. Queen's University, Canada University of Sherbrooke, Can.
1970 Hon. Deg. Loyola Univ.
1970 Hon. Deg. Clark Univ.
1971 Hon. Deg. Kalamazoo College
1971 Hon. Deg. Bard College
1971 Hon. Deg. Marquette University
1971 Hon. Deg. Williams College
1972 Hon. Deg. Catholic University
1972 Hon. Deg. University of Calgary
Awards
1940 John Phillips Memorial Award. American College of Physicians
1940 Mead Johnson Award. American Academy of Pediatrics
1958 Howard Taylor Ricketts Award. University of Chicago
1960 Passano Award. American Medical Association
1964 Robert Koch Centennial Award / Robert Koch Institute, Berlin
1964 Science Achievement Award. AMA
1966 Arches of Science Gold Medal and Prize / Pacific Science Center
1969 Pulitzer Prize
1969 Prix International de l'Institut de la Vie
Member of: National Academy of Sciences, American Philosophical Society, National Research Council, Sigma Xi, Century Club
Scope and Contents note
Materials include biographical information, bibliographies, awards and honors, conferences and lectures [agenda and programs], lab notebooks, interviews, clippings, audio and video tapes, photographs, manuscripts, typescripts, galley proofs, correspondence, reprints, reference notes, memorial materials [including letters of condolence to Mrs. Dubos], 80th Birthday Celebration and exhibition, and memorabilia.
Materials highlighting Dubos' work with antibiotics include the lab notebooks, awards and honors, and early reprints. His environmental interests are reflected in the plethora of conferences and lectures in which he participated, articles and books, awards and honors, and manuscripts.
The large number of photographs document Dubos' participation in these varied events, but many also depict aspects of his personal life, capturing Dubos at informal moments and with family members.
General note
Index to the René J. Dubos Papers
Additions to the Collection
96,101,133
Artwork
126
Audio Tapes
105-107, 133
Awards and Honors
9, 114
Bibliographies
5-6
Biographical Materials
1-4
Book Manuscripts and Book Related Materials
34-49 [see also 120-125]
Chemical Samples
81-85
Clippings
115-117 [see also 52-53]
Conferences and Lectures
118-119 [see also 56]
Correspondence
10-24, 128
The Despairing Optimist, Typescripts
50
80th Birthday Celebration and Exhibition
127
Film Reels (10)
RAC Film Vault
Glass Slides
99-100
Interviews, 1967-81 and Clippings
1939-82 52-53
Laboratory Notebooks
57-58
Manuscripts of Articles and Lectures; Annual Reports, ca. 1943-1982
25-33
Manuscripts, Typescripts and Galley Proofs
120-125 [see also 34-49], 133
Memorabilia
103, Packages 1-7
Memorabilia, Programs, and Misc. Items
130
Memorial Materials and Jean Dubos Materials
131
Misc. Materials - including correspondence, mss., reprints, clippings, memorabilia
86-88
Oversized Material including diplomas, citations, photographs, artwork, etc.
92-95
Oversized - plaques
104
Oversized
132
Packages (6) - primarily citations
not listed
Pasteur Biography (history of tuberculosis), working materials
78
Photographs (prints and negs) Scientific and Historical
60-63
Photographs
111-113 [see also 92-95]
Printed Materials, including on psychiatry
59 and art
Publicity Material for conferences, meetings, seminars, etc
56 [see also 118-119]
Reference Notes and Reference Materials
7-8
Reference Note Cards
76-77, 79-80
Reprints by Dubos, 1926-1985
64-70
Reprints by Dubos, Additional Copies
97-98
Reprints by Others
71-75
Reviews of R.J. Dubos Books
51
Scrapbooks
129
Subject Files
54-55
The Unseen World - Illustrations, including prints, negs., artwork
89-90
Volumes (2) removed to RAC Library
8/9/1988 not listed
Video Cassettes
108-110
Boxes Eliminated or Box Numbers Reassigned
7-8
Box numbers 7-8, formerly photographs circa 1928-1981, have been reassigned to Reference Notes and Reference Materials. The photographs are located in boxes 111-113.
91
Box 91 was eliminated and the audio tapes were integrated into boxes 105-107
103
Box 103 was eliminated. Slides from Avery book - placed in RAC slide collection, RG1150, Rm 107 RAC.
105
The Quest galley proof has been relocated to Box 124. Box 105 reassigned to Audio Tapes
Arrangement note
Boxes 1-104 are partially arranged, in chronological order within subjects. Make Full use of the index to the collection to locate materials. Additions to the collection, boxes 105-132, are standard processed and are arranged by subject and then in chronological order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 D851
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Environmental sciences; Antibiotics
- Biographical materials, 5" letter
  - Biographical materials, 1940-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes: Published articles about Dubos.
  - New York Times, clipping [re] Harvey Lecture, 1940 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Review of The Bacterial Cell in The Lancet, p 533.*, 1945 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Article [re] Selman Waksman by René J. Dubos, Time, 7 Nov. 1949, pp 71, 72, 74, 75, 76 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    *Correction 9 Mar. 87 Unsigned article, no evidence that Dubos is author.
  - Selman A. Waksman. Dr. René J. Dubos - A Tribute. JAMA 174 (1960) 503-505 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Who's Who In America 1942-1944 with addition to 1946, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical notes (holograph 3 pp) and c.v. (to ca 1960), circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - RU News Releases, 1959 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Current Biography, 1973 January; pp 1-14
    - Biographic Encyclopedia of Scientists and Technologists. René Jules Dubos. (In Italian), circa 1973; pp 10-12, (galley proof)
    - Medical World News, pp 77-82, 85-86. Medicine's Living History, 1975 May 5
  - Biographical, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes James Hirsch remarks on presentation of RU Honorary Degree to RJD, June 1975.
  - RU News Releases, 1976 1979 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Saul Benison. An oral history. René Dubos and the capsular polysaccharide of pneumococcus. Bulletin of the History of Medicine 50 (Winter 1976) 459-477 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kostelanetz, Richard. The five careers of René Dubos, 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - René Dubos. An outline [Prepared for receipt of the Wilder Penfield Award, Feb. 9, 1979 by the Vanier Institute], 1978 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - R.J. Dubos biographies, 1978 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    In: McGraw-Hill Modern Scientists and Engineers [Same text for each year but paging different.].
  - Jacques Dufresne. "René Dubos" (In French.) 5 pp text, 2 pp bibliography, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Colman McCarthy. "René Dubos - The Bright-Sider Who Believes in Man." Washington Post, pp?, 1981 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical sketches with additions to 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dedication to Dr. René Dubos. The Environmentalist 1 (1981) 179-181 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Materials removed from René J. Dubos's desk drawer (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes.
    - René J. Dubos's Social Security #
    - Technicians and secretaries in Dubos lab. Outline of René J. Dubos's scientific work. (In French), 1924-1964
    - List of lectures, honorary degrees and awards given by and received by René J. Dubos, 1963 September-1965 August
    - Handwritten comments possibly by student after an René J. Dubos lecture in California. [As identified by Mrs. Jean Dubos, May 1984], 1984 May
    - René Dubos signatures samples Personal telephone directory
    - Laboratory telephone extensions and names of René J. Dubos's lab
    - "Orientation" (re Dubos dept procedures), 6 pp photocopies
    - Handwritten notes by René J. Dubos, mostly on books, circa 1969-1980
  - Biographical. Personal history statements, circa 1947-1948 circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Obituary material, 1982 February 20-1983 January 1984 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes numerous newspaper and magazine articles; RU News and Notes; Joshua Lederberg report of RJD's death to RU Community; material re memorials honoring Dr. Dubos and Dubos mss published after his death.
  - Obituary, 1982 February 26 1982 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Cassette: Remarks by M.W. Chase. Professor Emeritus, RU on the memorial service for RJD. Recorded 26 Feb. and 3 Mar. 1982, RU Archives. Program; attendants.
  - Obituary materials: Dubos memorial talks at RU, 1982 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Photocopies supplied by Mrs. Jean Dubos.
    Includes talks by: Zanvil Cohn, Jean-Paul Escande, James Hirsch, Rollin D. Hotchkiss, William K. Reilly, Lewis Thomas.
  - Medical Tribune. Nathan Horowitz. "Remembering René Dubos: The True Environmentalist". pp 34, 38 [re] Dubos memorial at RU, 1982 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arthur M. Sackler (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - René Dubos: Scientist, Humanist, Advocate for "Joie de Vivre and Happiness for all Humankind. " re Dubos memorial service at RU and posthumous Humanitarian Award of the Arthur M. Sackler Foundation for the Arts, Sciences and Humanities. (AMS Award.) Accepted by Mrs. Jean Dubos (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bibliographies, 1982 July (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    Includes Computer search for articles by RJD. [See descriptive inventory of Dubos bibliographies in folder 8].
    [*SEE BOXES 5 and 6 FOR ALL THE R.J. DUBOS BIBLIOGRAPHIES]. Bibliographies removed for recataloging.
  - René J. Dubos's 70th birthday, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bibliographies and Reprint index (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Monthly Minder (kept by Carol Moberg), 5"
    - 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (kept by RJD).
    - 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- RU News and Notes, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Includes:.
  - 1. Dubos launches City's bicentennial, 1975 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes galley.
  - For Jan. 1976 NEWS AND NOTES. re Dubos receiving Cullum Geographical Medal of the American Geographical Society on Nov. 24, 1975, Galley only (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - For April 1976 NEWS AND NOTES. re Dubos receiving honorary degree from St. Peter's University, Jersey City, NJ, Galley only (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vol 7 2. Dubos shares $150,000 ecology prize, 1976 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vol 8 1. New Dubos book on "The Professor", 1976 November (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - For Feb. 1978 NEWS AND NOTES. re Dubos delivering Kate Connor Memorial lecture, 1978 January 10; Galley only (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Various excerpts of galleys from French publications by René J. Dubos (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Classified as to a subject with reference next to passage within the subject. [As identified by Mrs. Jean Dubos, May 23, 1984].
- Institute to University. 75th anniversary colloquium 8 June 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Booklet includes RJD article "Fess Avery: The man and the scientist".
- René J. Dubos's 80th birthday celebration (Box 3, Folder 6)
- René J. Dubos's Memberships. Membership certificates; correspondence and printed material, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Dubos Slide Index (photocopy) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Thomas L. Wenger. René Dubos: Scientist and Natural Philosopher. A senior thesis submitted to History Department Princeton University for BA, 1965 April; Bound photocopy (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Steven Schwartz. Medical Philosophy: A Dubosian Perspective, 1970 May (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Toby Nagurney. Interview with René Dubos re "So Human an Animal" [NPI], 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Charles Elkins. 1974. René Dubos: Environmental Crisis and Scientific Responsibility. Paper delivered by Charles Elkins, Milwaukee, National Popular Culture Assoc meeting, Science and Literature seminar, 1974 May 2 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Includes correspondence from Elkins/Dubos with Dubos handwritten reply.
- Paul Schwartzman, A biography of René J. Dubos. 26 pp photocopy. For History of Ecology course, Johns Hopkins University, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Includes 2 items correspondence between Schwartz and Dubos.
- Dianne Cmich. Selected quotes from Dubos books, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Carel B. German. Ms re Dubos, undated; pp 3-7; lacking pp 1-2. Photocopy (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Bruce Piasecki, The Dangers of Environmental Ambivalence: An Analysis of René Dubos' "The Wooing of Earth", circa 1980?; 11 pp photocopy (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Faculty Personnel Files, 1927-1977 1979 (and published material to 1976) (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 3"
  Description, with selected items noted.
  - Correspondence, 1927-1929 1934-1935 1938 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Selman A. Waksman re Dubos, 1927 June 7
    - Dubos acknowledges appointment as Fellow at Hospital, 1927 June 21
    - Announcement of marriage to Marie Louise Bonnet, 1934 March 23
    - re Symposium on bacterial enzymes for Society of American Bacteriologists meeting, 1938
    - Proposal, OSRD contract, circa 1942
    - Correspondence with Jean Porter, 1942
    - Dubos decision to go to Harvard, 1942
    - Offer and acceptance of Member at RIMR, 1943
  - Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re technicians, 1944
    - Estimate of Dr. Dubos' Laboratory, Rooms 309-311, New North Building, 1944
    - Herald Tribune clipping re Tyrothricine, 1944 October 18
    - Control of Virulent tubercle bacilli, 1946
    - Appointment as editor of JEM, 1946
  - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Honorary doctorate from U. Liége, Belgium, 1947
    - James Hirsch, 1949
    - Miembro Correspondiente Extranjero of the Academia de Ciencias Fisicas, Matematicas y Naturales of Caracas, Venezuela, 1950
    - Studies on BCG vaccine, Public Health Service, 1950
  - Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - re Dr. Waksman and incorporation of Foundation for Microbiology, 1951
    - re James Hirsch, 1951 1952
    - re Julius Marmur, 1952
    - re David Weiss, 1952
  - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Copy of A.V. Hill lecture sent to D.W. Bronk, 1955
    - D.W. Bronk formal invitation and regrets to National University of Ireland (D.Sc. to Dubos), 1955
    - Announcement for Smoker and Scientific Exhibits at RIMR in connection with meeting of Society of American Bacteriologists, 1955
    - Immunizing antigen of tubercle bacilli and Cornell University Medical School (Walsh McDermott), 1956
    - re Dr. W. Kurylowicz, U. Warsaw, 1956
    - Dubos/Bronk on philosophy of public health, with 3 pp. draft expressing present attitude, 1957 January 3
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Bronk/Dubos on RI sponsoring Christmas Lectures like Royal Institution of London, 1958 January 1
    - re Curtis Williams, 1958
    - Dubos/Nelson Rockefeller. Views on USA aiding protein nutrition problem, 1958
    - Award from Dutch Assoc of Lung Physicians, 1958
    - re International Congress of Microbiology, Stockholm, 1958 August
    - re Dubos attending International Congress in Rio de Janeiro and International Symp in Freiburg, Summer 1959
    - Honorary Sc. D., University of Brazil, 1960
    - Bronk/Dubos (Telegram). Congratulations on superb 1959 Christmas Lectures, 1959 2 January 1960
      Includes other 1960 correspondence re Lectures.
    - re Passano Foundation Award, 1960
      Includes printed materials.
    - Flinn/Dubos. List of members of Faculty, Guest Investigators and Students holding appointments on medical staff of Hospital, 1960 May 27
    - Dubos address to graduating class of Cornell Medical College and CU-NYH School of Nursing included in printed program, 1960 June 1
    - re R.W. Schaedler, 1960 1962
    - Marlin/Kone, 1960 August 26
      Includes ms on Dubos and Passano Award.
    - Outline of Brookhaven Pegram lectures used for "The Dreams of Reason", 1960
    - Silliman Lectures at Yale, 1960
    - May Sarton's poems in memory of Father, George Sarton, 1960
  - Correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Dubos/Bronk re invitations to attend conferences and lecture, 1961
    - Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters, Yeshiva University, 1961
    - New York Times Book Review clipping, Letter to the Editor, on "The Dreams of Reasons", 1961 October 1
    - Campus Bulletin, University of Calif., San Francisco Medical Center clipping re 1962 Herzstein Lectures, 1962 February
    - Holiday Lectures in Cincinnati (RI Christmas Lectures), 1962
    - re Condon lectures; London International Congress on Symbiosis; Penrose Lecture, 1962
    - Salmon Lectures, 1962 December; Printed announcement
    - Phi Beta Kappa Award for "The Unseen World", 1963
    - AMA Scientific Achievement Award, 1964
      Includes clippings from Medical Tribune.
    - re "Man Adapting" from Silliman Lectures, 1964
    - Dubos/Bronk, re views on enlarging scope of biological studies at RI, 1964 November 16
    - Phi Beta Kappa News Release re annual Phi Beta Kappa-Sigma Xi address, Montreal, 1964 December 30
    - Doctor of Laws, University of Calif, 1965
    - re 1966 Colby College commencement address and honorary degree, 1965
    - re Merrill Chase, Jules Hirsch and Zanvil Cohn, 1965
    - AMA Lecture, 1965
      Includes typescript (photocopy) of p 3 of lecture re RI.
    - Bronk/Dubos, re "Man Adapting", 1965 November 10
    - re Kansas City address, 1965
  - Correspondence, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - re cold room alterations, 1966
    - Dubos/Bronk re faculty members salary increases, 1966
    - Science and Public Policy seminar, 1966 May 26
      Includes Dubos presentation, typescript (photocopy).
    - Arches of Science Award, 1966
      Includes newspaper clippings.
    - Philip Handler/Bronk. Reasons for not participating in Oklahoma City exercises, 1966 September 27
    - Phi Beta Kappa Award for "Man Adapting", 1966
    - F.L. Stone/Dubos. Compliments on chairing workshop at Conference on Comparative Medicine, 1967 March 6; (carbon copy)
    - re Chi-Jen Lee, 1967 1973
    - re Dubos lecture at opening of Institute for Science in Human Affairs, Columbia University, 1967
    - re Two Cultures Award, Flushing High School, New York City, 1967
    - re Richard L. Costello, 1968 1972
    - Astronautics and Aeronautics editorial quoting René J. Dubos, 1968 October; Clipping
    - Seitz/Dubos and others. Exchange re animal facilities improvement at RU, 1968
    - re Pulitzer prize for "So Human an Animal", 1969; Clippings
    - re Glenn Paulson, 1969 1972
    - Dubos/Seitz re RU policy concerning Professors Emeriti and suggestions, 1969 December 16
    - Dubos/Seitz, 1970 March 6
      Includes Dubos presentation on environmental research and teaching at Argonne University Association (photocopied typescript).
    - Dubos/Seitz. re Dubos participation in Campaign GM and GM's environmental responsibilities, 1970 April 13
    - New York Times clipping re Dubos remarks at McGraw-Hill Conference, 1970 June 18
    - New York Times clipping re Dubos heading Environmental Studies program at SUNY Purchase, 1970 November 12
  - Correspondence, 1971-1977 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - James G. Hirsch [memo] re Cohn-Hirsch dept, circa 1971 January?
    - re Dr. Subramanian, 1971
    - Croton-Cortlandt News clipping, re Dubos lecture in Ossining, 1971 January 21
    - re Dubos chairing independent group of consultants at Stockholm, UN International Conf on the Human Environment, 1972
      Includes Dubos ms Introduction, to "Only One Earth" with Seitz comments. Also includes Maurice Strong ms Preface.
    - New York Times Magazine, clip of article by John Culhame. "En Garde, Pessimists: Enter René Dubos", 1971 October 17
    - Seitz/Dubos exchange re Dubos 1972-73 budget, 1971 1972
    - New York Times clipping re Dubos award of First Institute of Life prize, 1972 May 3
    - re Dubos participation in Pasteur celebration, 1972 1973
    - re Honorary Life Membership, New York Academy of Sciences, 1973
    - New York Times clipping, printed apology to Dubos and others, 1974 June 13
    - Honorary D. Sc from RU, 1975
    - re Florence Sabin, 1975
    - Dubos/Seitz, re René Dubos Environmental Forum, 1977 August 30
    - re Dubos and Meadows discussion on world wide problem of starvation at RU, 1979. [Jules Hirsch/RU Colleagues]
- Application for Staff Appointment, signed, 1927 June 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Individual record card (Box 4, Folder 10)
- C.V., 1941 March 24 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Who's Who in America (copy), 1942-1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Publications [Numbers 1-179], 1928-1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Clippings and Publicity, 1939-1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photographs (Portraits) (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Biographies, News from The RI, RU, 1959 1966 1971 1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Obituary/Memorial Service for R.J. Dubos (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Bibliographies, In 2-2½" letter size boxes
  - Bibliographies
    - Bibliography "Master Bibliography", 1926-1982; 44 pp. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies. Computer Search, 1982 July 28 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bibliographies. Lectures, Addresses, Speeches, 1943-1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)